<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Sayantan Khan's Blog - personal</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2020-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Summer 2020 update</title><link href="/update-summer-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Sayantan Khan</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-09-26:/update-summer-2020.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another 9 months have gone by without a blog post, and this time I don't even have lack of time as an excuse
my lack of writing. This summer turned out to be quite different from what I had planned, which probably goes
to show one shouldn't plan too far …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another 9 months have gone by without a blog post, and this time I don't even have lack of time as an excuse
my lack of writing. This summer turned out to be quite different from what I had planned, which probably goes
to show one shouldn't plan too far ahead, in this day and age. I figured it might be a good time make a list of
what I did this summer, and contrast that with what I was planning to do, before I forget the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was supposed to begin my summer with a conference at Haifa, but that of course didn't pan out, given the
pandemic. The expectation was to follow up the conference by learning more Lie group theory and associated
dynamics and representation theory, along the lines of what Hee Oh does, but I never got around to doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I did manage to get some math done this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I worked with my undergraduate collaborator CP&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and my postdoc mentor BW, as a part of AW's REU, and
managed to prove some asymptotic bounds on the minimal stretch factors of certain pseudo-Anosov maps. BW is
still reviewing the paper right now, and fixing up some sections, but hopefully the preprint should be up on
ArXiV soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also have enough theorems to write up a paper on the project I have been working on since February. Writing
it up might be a bit of a nightmare, given how long it's been since the earlier results. But hopefully I should
have something up on ArXiV in a month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also learnt enough Teichmüller theory and Teichmüller dynamics to pass my prelims, which is definitely
  good. I am no longer as afraid of complex analytic Teichmüller theory as I used to be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer was fairly productive in terms of programming: I went through most of
&lt;a href="https://www.nand2tetris.org/"&gt;nand2tetris&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. designed a 16-bit computer from scratch, starting with the
NAND gates, going up to assembly, followed with an intermediate VM language. I skipped writing a compiler for
compiling Scheme to the intermediate VM language, because the Scheme specification is more complicated than I
thought. I followed that up with trying to write a x86-64 microkernel in Rust, but x86-64 has a lot of details
to debug, so I shelved that project as well. Right now, I am writing some userspace filesystem code that
should be easier to debug, given that it doesn't work at the kernel level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Climbing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My climbing goals have suffered the most since the pandemic began. Originally, I was planning on getting my
lead climbing certification this summer, and progress to climbing 5.10+ or 5.11- outdoors, but none of that
happened after the gyms closed down. I've only climbed twice outside since then, and my footwork, among other
things, has obviously degraded. I'm just hoping that once the gyms open up again, I can recover to the point
where I was in a month or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figure it's a good idea to not name people I know personally in my blog.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="math"></category><category term="programming"></category><category term="climbing"></category></entry><entry><title>Summer 2018 update</title><link href="/update-summer-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Sayantan Khan</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-06-02:/update-summer-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm getting lazy. I thought I would be posting more often once the summer holidays started
but May came and went with nary a post. In my defence, I was fairly busy, dealing with
the usual bureaucratic nonsense that comes with leaving your institution for good and moving
to another …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm getting lazy. I thought I would be posting more often once the summer holidays started
but May came and went with nary a post. In my defence, I was fairly busy, dealing with
the usual bureaucratic nonsense that comes with leaving your institution for good and moving
to another country. I also started learning algebraic geometry seriously, and will continue to
focus on it for a major part of the summer. Doing only math gets boring really quick though,
so I'll interleave the math sessions with some coding. I started learning &lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;,
and got sidetracked for a while by Emacs. But before I talk about Rust and Emacs, I'll quickly
outline my math plans for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Math in Summer 2018&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that I'll probably be doing more differential geometry at UMichigan, I figured I'd take
a break from that in the summer. In fact, I decided to stay as far as I can from analysis as well;
in fact, anything that involves taking derivatives, or dealing with inequalities. I considered
studying combinatorics, number theory or algebraic geometry, none of which I know anything about. I was also initially
encouraged by the fact that they seem as far from analysis as possible. That, of course, was astonishing
naïveté and ignorance on my part, because &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generating_function"&gt;generating functions&lt;/a&gt; 
crop up everywhere in combinatorics, and sooner or later, one would have to show one of these
things converges in some small ball in the complex plane, and then we would be back to doing analysis.
That left number theory and algebraic geometry. Analytic number theory was out of the question, so the choice
essentially boiled down to algebraic number theory or algebraic geometry. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algebraic_number_theory"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;
for algebraic
number theory had one picture, and that was a picture of a textbook. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algebraic_geometry"&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; for 
algebraic geometry had three, and they were all images of algebraic varieties. That essentially made my decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started reading Fulton's &lt;a href="www.math.lsa.umich.edu/~wfulton/CurveBook.pdf"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on algebraic curves and assumed
that would be enough. However, I learnt of an algebraic geometry summer school happening in IISER Pune, and signed
up for it immediately. But that necessitated a change of pace as they require the attendees to have studied the first chapter of Hartshorne's book
in excruciating detail. Currently, I'm reading both Fulton and Hartshorne
simultaneously and I'll probably also resume doing the exercises in Atiyah-Macdonald's commutative algebra book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal goal is to build up some sort of Rosetta stone like glossary for translating stuff from algebraic
to differential geometry and vice versa. I'll write more about it once I've made some progress. The long term
goal is to learn complex algebraic geometry, where I'll be able to use techniques from both differential and
algebraic geometry. But this will probably take some time, perhaps a year or longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rust and Emacs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been hearing about Rust a lot these days, especially after the release of Firefox Quantum, which
apparently has large parts written in Rust. I thought it would be nice to pick a low level language
like Rust. It's certainly more suitable than Python for writing always running daemons, given that
each individual Python program spins up VM that takes up 20 to 30 megabytes for simple tasks like
scanning log files or fetching mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I've learnt the basics of Rust's &lt;a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/second-edition/ch04-00-understanding-ownership.html"&gt;ownership model&lt;/a&gt;,
and I seem to get the basic idea, although I'll only know that for sure if I use it build something fairly
complex. I'm racking my brains thinking about what to write: I've considered writing a compression program,
which might be fun, but I'm afraid it might be a bit too ambitious. I guess I'll figure it out sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned earlier, I got sidetracked for a while by Emacs when I was setting it up as a Rust
environment. As it often happens, instead of just using Emacs as a tool to write code in, I started
playing around with it instead. Of course, the fact that Emacs essentially is a Lisp environment
only got me more distracted. I learnt some Emacs Lisp from this really well written &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/eintr.html"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; 
and it was rather fun. In fact, just a few days ago, I sent out a &lt;a href="https://github.com/rakanalh/emacs-dashboard/pull/70"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; 
extending an Emacs package I use. I'll be thrilled if it gets accepted. Emacs is really nice this way because
there's practically no barrier between using the editor to examining and changing the source code of the various components
that make up the editor. I cannot imagine doing the same in Vim. I'm really glad I switched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for the summer update. I'll post more (and I hope with greater frequency), hopefully stuff related to algebraic
geometry and Rust (and maybe even Emacs).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry></feed>